<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Considerable considerations to be considered of: with Christian queries, requisite to be inquired of, in this juncture of time, and conjunction of dis-joyned interests, now to be conjoyned in a counsil disjoyned, and without head or feet. All which ought seriously and sadly to be laid to heart, 1. Some of them by all in generall, in whom there is any honesty, as men, loyalty, as subiects, piety, as Christians. 2. Some other of them by Presbyterians in speciall. 3. Other some by those that are to joyn in the counsel in particular. Collected by him that is a lover of truth, loyalty, and the subiects liberty, both for his own, and others better satisfaction. / By S.L. minister of the gospel.</title>
            <author>S. L.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88784</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866439</idno>
  <idno type="VID">118714</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240922002</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L59</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E817_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207384</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866439</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99866439e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88784)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118714)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 124:E817[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Considerable considerations to be considered of: with Christian queries, requisite to be inquired of, in this juncture of time, and conjunction of dis-joyned interests, now to be conjoyned in a counsil disjoyned, and without head or feet. All which ought seriously and sadly to be laid to heart, 1. Some of them by all in generall, in whom there is any honesty, as men, loyalty, as subiects, piety, as Christians. 2. Some other of them by Presbyterians in speciall. 3. Other some by those that are to joyn in the counsel in particular. Collected by him that is a lover of truth, loyalty, and the subiects liberty, both for his own, and others better satisfaction. / By S.L. minister of the gospel.</title>
                  <author>S. L.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeer 1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Christianity --  Essence, genius, nature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life --  Protestant authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Presbyterianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118714:1"/>
            <p>CONSIDERABLE CONSIDERATIONS To be considered of<hi>:</hi> WITH CHRISTIAN QUERIES, Requisite to be inquired of, In this Juncture of time, and Conjunction of dis-joyned Interests, now to be conjoyned in a Council dis-joyned, and without head or feet.</p>
            <p>All which ought seriously and sadly to be laid to heart,
<list>
                  <item>1. Some of them by all in generall, in whom there is any Honesty, as men, Loyalty, as Subiects, Piety, as Christians.</item>
                  <item>2. Some other of them by Presbyterians in speciall.</item>
                  <item>3. Othersome by those that are to joyn in the Counsel in particular.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Collected by him that is a Lover of Truth, Loyalty, and the Subiects Liberty, both for his own, and others better satisfaction.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 1.1.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Blessed is the man that walketh not in the counsel of the ungodly.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>ISAI. 8.10.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take counsel together, and it shall come to nought.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>PROV. 12.3.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>A man cannot be established by Wickedness.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>ISAI. 30.7.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore have I cried concerning this; their strength is to sit still.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>JOB. 5. 27.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Loe this, we have searched it, so it is, hear it, and know thou it for thy good.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>By S. L. Minister of the Gospel.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeer 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118714:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F these Considerations and Queries could upon several inquisitions and inquiries, have inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out any, (upon any reasonable considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) that would (Midwife-like) have lent them a helping hand to have helped them into the world in time, they then might have been (at least) to some a word in season; and had not run, which now they have, the hazard either of perishing in the womb, or dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the birth, or of being born out of due time, as now they may seem to bee: But what may befall them, they much sear not, nor much consider their own disadvantage, so they may advantage thee, and advance any thing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the glory of God, and the safety and setling of these three Kingdomes in peace and truth; which is all (the all in all) which these Considerations have taken into their consideration in this their undertaking, and adventure, in venturing abroad.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>VALE.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118714:2"/>
            <head>Cosiderable Considerations, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Iirst, by all in generall. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether those persons, who being not lawfully called, according to any Laws of God or Men; to places of Power, Dominion and Authority; but doe set up themselves in the place of <hi>Magistrace; Rule</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and usurp the <hi>higher power,</hi> be not such as God hath branded for their wickedness, by <hi>Hab. chap.</hi> 1, <hi>ver.</hi> 6, 7 9, 10, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi> let all consider.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Whether those persons that are illegally set up by others, and those also that set them up; having no <hi>lawful authority</hi> so to do, bee not all of them sinfull and wicked, in so doing? And whether for their sinful wickedness in doing so, they are not such as God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of, <hi>Hos.</hi> 8, 4? would be considered.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Whether any persons unlawfully impowred, can lawfully be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed? considering what <hi>Paul</hi> saith to him, that is generally held a <hi>Ʋsurper, Acts</hi> 23.3. but not so to others, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.10. and <hi>Acts</hi> 26.2 especially <hi>ver.</hi> 24, 25. And whether any can act by vertue of any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, or other ways under them, without owning of them? And whether <hi>obedience to, acting by,</hi> and <hi>owning of them,</hi> be not to become guilty of <hi>Ephraims</hi> sin, for which he was <hi>oppressed and broken in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Hos.</hi> 5.11? <hi>(Command</hi> there cannot bee meant touching the Calves in particular, as some say; for, as for them, there was none gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, (see the place) but <hi>Ephraims</hi> obeying and acting in general, or what <hi>Jeroboam</hi> commanded, as the word <hi>command</hi> imports and implies) and then whether <hi>peoples submitting to such, be to submit for the Lords sake, as</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. or for <hi>their own sakes,</hi> should be considered.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Whether that command of <hi>God,</hi> which commands <hi>obedience</hi> and <hi>allegiance</hi> to persons lawfully authorized, and legally by <hi>Lawes and Oaths</hi> established, do not countermand and forbid <hi>obedience to Ʋsurpers and Traytors,</hi> seeing an affirmative <hi>command</hi> contains in, and under it, a negative, <hi>honor the King</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17. This is the affirmative <hi>command,</hi> and this we must do; dishonor the <hi>King</hi> which is the negative forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in, and under the affirmative, this therefore we may not do: ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor the King, and another also that is not King, with the Kings ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118714:3"/> this we cannot do, <hi>Mat:</hi> 6.24. Seeing now we see that honour both we cannot<hi>:</hi> dishonor the <hi>King</hi> we may not; and, if we honor a <hi>No-King,</hi> dishonor the <hi>King</hi> we must. Whether therefore we are not forbid to honor a <hi>no King,</hi> by honoring whom, we shall una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably dishonor a lawful <hi>King,</hi> which we are forbidden, being the negative countermanded under the affirmative command; command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to honor him would be wel considered of. This truth is likewise exprest in this like expression, <hi>Give to Caesar, the things that are Caesars, Mat:</hi> 22: 21. He that will give <hi>Caesar</hi> his due, and will give <hi>Caesars</hi> due to another also, and yet think he shal not deal unduly with <hi>Caesar,</hi> must of necessity either reconcile Contradictions, (which is impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) or acknowledg himself a trespassor in the things of <hi>Caesar,</hi> and a transgressor of <hi>Gods command</hi> touching <hi>Caesars things,</hi> and so justifie this truth, <hi>That Gods command of obedience to persons lawfully, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termands it to persons unlawfully impowred.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 Seeing it is Commanded to render to all their dues, <hi>Rom:</hi> 1.3.7. and that <hi>obedience, honor,</hi> and <hi>loyalty</hi> are the undoubted dues of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons lawfully impowred in the <hi>higher power,</hi> for whom in especial, (and in the first place) these are in that place given in command. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, seeing it is likewise required, <hi>To do to all men all things what soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they would that men should do to them, Mat</hi> 7, 12 and it is certain, that theere is not any in the world, that would, that what is his by right should by violence and wrong, be taken from him and given to another; Then whether he that gives to another than <hi>Caesar,</hi> those things which are <hi>Caesars,</hi> is not a transgressor against the aforesaid general <hi>Command, Rom.</hi> 13. 7. and Christs <hi>Precept</hi> in particular, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 21? And whether they that do what they would not have done to them (let every loyal subject make a Kings case his own) are not also notorious transgressors of that grand <hi>Christian Command</hi> and <hi>Rule, Which is the Law and the Prophets, Mat,</hi> 7, 12? should by Christians be inquired of and considered.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Whether those that by <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Oaths</hi> stand in the relation and condition of <hi>Subjects,</hi> (and from which no human power can absolve them) to a person or persous established lawfully in the higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; If they shall yet serve, observe, and obey a person, or persons unlawfully by force and usurpation, usurping the higher power, must not unavoidably, either be guilty of the sins of disobedience and perjury, by not obeying the lawful, or obey both, and so by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king possible Christs impossibility, <hi>No man can serve two Masters, Mat.</hi> 6.24. make Christ a lyar?</p>
            <p n="7">7 Whether those that complain of, and judg another for taking
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118714:3"/> away their rights unrighteously, and yet themselves are either ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of, or partakers with others, in taking away another mans; do not in so doing condemn themselves? as <hi>Rom!</hi> 2. 1:</p>
            <p n="8">8 Whether there be not one and the same standing rule of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness and justice for all, by which every one respectively hath a like equal right and propriety in, and to, every thing hee hath and holdeth? And if so, as certainly it is, whether Kings lawfully called, have not as good and iust a title and right to their Crowns, as Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects have to their estates? And then whether those that do, or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly suffer any thing in prejudice to them, doe not thereby doe as much and the very same for substance, against themselves, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by teach others to do to themselves, as themselves have done to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? would be considered.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Whether force and power can make a lawfull title? it cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy it, all know and <hi>contrariorum eadem est ratio,</hi> force may thrust out of possession as it did <hi>Naboth,</hi> and bring into possession, as it did <hi>Ahab,</hi> when he killed and took possession, 1. <hi>King</hi> 21. 19. but neither put him into, nor the other out of a just title; if it can then <hi>Absalon</hi> was no rebell, when <hi>David</hi> was driven away; <hi>Zimri</hi> no traytor when he had kild <hi>Elah;</hi> &amp; <hi>Athaliah</hi> no usurper, when she had destroyd all the kings seed; Then the theft of the theef, the oppression of the oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor, the tyrany of the tyrant, &amp; the rreason of the traytor, are not sins, &amp; then God hath lost one of his ten commandments, and every man, that meets with a man stronger then himself, hath lost all his right, title, and propriety to all he hath, all those great conquests in and over <hi>Canaan</hi> by the Isralites, gained only a possession, but made no title; that they had from God before by his gift <hi>Pas:</hi> 35. 11, 12.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Whether to argu from the permission of God to Cods approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, affirmatively, and to conclude, because God suffers such and such things, things most execrable and impious, that therefore God hath done them, or allows them, be not (which is yet the logick of these times) a'most blaspheamous conclusion? concluding full against the justice, righteousness and holiness of the Lord, who is a God, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then when he sees to suffer it, of purer eyes than to behold ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity <hi>Hab.</hi> 1. 13. viz to approve it, and whether this doth not charge upon God, all the wickedness in the world, formerly, and now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted? as the treason of <hi>Iudas,</hi> the rebellion of <hi>Cerah,</hi> the murther of <hi>Cain,</hi> and the blasphemies of the woman full of names of blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. 3. with all the like wickedness; done? and whether they that do so for God then did, and now doeth, suffer all those, and all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118714:4"/> these abominable things to be done, I say whether they by such blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieamous conclusions, do not most impiously and blaspheamously make God the author, and actor or all these abominable abominations which he only suffers would be considered of.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Whether they that pretend so much to, and for, Christ, and Christianity, profess so much holiness and piety; and (as if nothing but purity and sanctity had gone to their composiiton) call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sleves Saints, the Godly party, &amp;c. Yet.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There most Christian Actions, as appeares by their acting are to set up themselves, not the things of Christ; to seek (meerly, or mostly) their own, not others good, and do to others, what they would not should be done to themselves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their most Christian arguments, if we may believe their own words, are drawn not from Christian equity, which they ought to do, 1. <hi>Thes.</hi> 4.1. But from unchristian power, what they can do <hi>Mich.</hi> 2.1. not from the justness of their cause, but from the length of their swords, for Christians, and Saints in profession, to justifie their actions by power and force, is most unsaint-like, and unchristian; to say with her (in such a case as that) dost thou now govern the Kingdome of <hi>Israel?</hi> or with him (in any case) what wee cannot do by right, wee will (because we can) do by might: or, to act with them who frame mischief by a Law: or to destroy Law, to do mischie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vously, wickedly, <hi>cum previlegio,</hi> are none of them, if certain, the words, works or arguments of Saints, unless of St. <hi>Jezebel,</hi> St. <hi>Iudas,</hi> St. <hi>Julian</hi> the Apostate or St. <hi>Cain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Their most unchristian suffering and tollerating, those intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble errors, Doctrines of Devills, damnable herisies, abominable blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, and inconscientious liberties, which these Saints suffer and tollerate: (they say for tender, the truth is for, feared consciences) and which shew, that in them there is as little of Christ, christianity, or sanctity, as either of the former: Therefore whether these preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders (the premises considered) for all their pretences be not such, as he that is holy and true, tells us he will make them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.7.9. such as he that is truth it self saith of them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 27. 28. such as <hi>Paul</hi> speaking by the spirit of truth, speaks of them, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 2. 3. 4. 5. and <hi>Tit,</hi> 1, 16. and such as those holy Prophets complained of in their times, <hi>Isa.</hi> 48.1. 2. <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.10. <hi>Mich.</hi> 2. 1, 2, and <hi>Heb.</hi> 2, 5. to 10. is very considerable, ant if so (as most certainly such they are) then what assurance that there is truth and sincerity in them, in any thing they say? what hopes, that they will do, any good, to others
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118714:4"/> in anything they do; and what expectation, that the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness should be in them, that they should make good, those goodly shews and professions which they make, touching the glory of God, any can have, hope, or expect from them, would also be considered.</p>
            <p n="12">12 Whether the Apost. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. requires obedience to all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons that are in present power (however impowerd) for this reason, that it is said, the powers that are, are ordained of God as some say? or whether he rather intend no such thing, as the truth is he doth not, beeing rightly understood? and whether rightly to understand him, we must not consider?</p>
            <p n="1">1 That by Power and powers there, is meant that Authority, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistracy, Dominion, and Government which God hath ordained to be in, and exercised by, some persons, by vertue of which they rule and Govern all others under them:</p>
            <p n="2">2 That it is called powers in the plurall number, because many and divers, as Monarchie, Aristocracy, and Democracy.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That obedience is required to these in the plurall number, powers, because, all and every one of these, whethersoever it be, and whereso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever exercised, it must be obeyed.</p>
            <p n="4">4, That it is said, that there is no power, in the singular number, but it is of God, to shew that every one of them a part single, and in particular<hi>:</hi> wheher Monarchy, Aristocracy, Democracy, is a power and ordained of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object. Peter</hi> calls it an ordinance of man, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> Whether of these (when and where none of these are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy established) shall be set up and exercised amongst men, in this or that nation and people, men may choose, and set up which, and whether of them they will, and so may be said to be an ordinance of man, as <hi>Pet.</hi> rules it, but the power and authority it self, which of them soever it be<hi>:</hi> This is of God ever, as <hi>Paul</hi> saith.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That, that to which every soul must be subject, is said to be power, and powers in the abstract, not person or persons impowred in the concreete: to shew.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The distinction and difference between the thing and the person Magistracie, and the Magistrate: and that the power and the person are distinguished, and differ, as <hi>Joh.</hi> 19. 10. 11. I have power where is both, person and power. So in this place also, where the thing (viz. the authority and government is called power, <hi>ver.</hi> 1 The persons au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized and governing, are called rulers and Ministers of God, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. 4. which many ignorantly confound, as if all one in that place: to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118714:5"/> which may be added that in the Epist. to <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 1. where are both al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the power, the authority and government, is of God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, although the persons in it be oft set in by men, either of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elves as usurpers are; and <hi>Athaliah</hi> was 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 22. 10. <hi>l.</hi> or by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as other traytours as <hi>Hos.</hi> 8. 4 with 1 <hi>King</hi> 12. 27. compared,</p>
            <p n="3">3 That subjection is always to be yeilded to the power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that being ever of God, God ordained it: and to it every soul must be subject <hi>ver.</hi> 1<hi>:</hi> But for the person exerciseing of it.</p>
            <p n="1">ii If they be lawfully impowerd: yet if they command unlawfull things, then wee ought to obey God, rather than men: <hi>Act.</hi> 5.29.</p>
            <p n="2">2 If they have unlawfully usurped the power, then know that <hi>Ephraim</hi> was oppressed and broken in judgment for obeying <hi>Hos</hi> 5.11.</p>
            <p>And this truths holds even in the then <hi>Roman power:</hi> it (the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) with all other powers was ordained of God<hi>:</hi> and to it (the power) as wel as to any other, subjection was requiried of God<hi>:</hi> But what obedience was required to the then Roman persons in power; if such and so badly impowerd, as some say, but prove not (yet from it would justifie what is bad enough) would be wel considered; especially seeing <hi>Ephraim</hi> was broken in judgment for obeying the ike, if they say truly of it; and seeing it was the power, not the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in it, to which obedience was there required.</p>
            <p n="6">6 That the abstract power, is not put for the concrete, the person im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powred, as some say is evident for the power and the person impow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red are distinguished and several, as was even now shewed; and is further manifested, ver. 3: where it is said, wilt thou then not be afraid of the power, do that which is good<hi>:</hi> indeed hee that doth good need not fear the power; for it protects him, he shall have praise of it, ver: 3: yet may and had need sometimes, fear the person impowerd, who would for doing good destroy him, as usurpers and traytors do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obejct.</hi> It is said so of persons impowerd too; That Rulers (so per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons as wel as powers) are not a terror to good works, ver<hi>:</hi> 3: <hi>ergo:</hi> this makes no distinction &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans:</hi> That which is spoken of the power, which they that do well need not fear; this is spoken absolutely; there can in well doing be no fear at all, of it<hi>:</hi> but that which is spoken of rulers, that they are not a terror to good works, this is spoken with limitation, viz. that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118714:5"/>
               <hi>Godly rulers are not, ungodly ought not to be,</hi> and all rulers that rule according to this power which God hath ordained, are not, cannot bee; but all rulers do not so rule, so the distinction between power and person, stands here still, which is also further cleard in the—</p>
            <p n="7">7 That power, authority, and government, are for good, and do good ever, even amongst the worst, and most wicked that are, who else would both be worse, and do worse, and become such as <hi>Hab.</hi> speakes of, Chap. 1. Ver. 14. and yet not withstanding, the good that comes by power, persons impowerd oft times are bad enough (for usurpers and tyrants) and do badly enough: therefore we must distinguish still between power and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, the ignorant confounding of which, and that by colour oftl is place, hath brought in and continued a word of confusion and wickedness amongst us, in justifying persons unlawfully impowerd, by and from this lawfull power which God ordained.</p>
            <p n="8">8 That the word <hi>are,</hi> about which many make so much adoo, will bee to little purpose, and to as little advantage to their cause, if wee consider,</p>
            <p n="1">1 That the word <hi>are,</hi> is not here a sign of the presenttence, but a verb, and signifies not the present being of a thing, but the reall being of a thing: therefore cannot prove as they fancie and faine that they that always are in power, have right to the power they are in, but that the powers that are, are things real, against filthy dreamers that despise them, <hi>Iud.</hi> ver. 8. and these that slandred the Gospel, as destructive to Magistracy, which it main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and requires obedience to.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Of what it is that the Apost. saith<hi>—that are:</hi> He saith not the persons that are, but the powers that are, so then all the good the word are doeth them in repeating of it so ost, the powers that are, the powers that are, by which they so greatly triumph without any victory; I say all the good the word are doth them, is to shew how ignorant they are, and grosly mistaken, to mistake powers for persons; and how absurd they are from thence to conclude a most notorious falsehood of obedience to men, from or rather against the Apost inspired truth, requiring obedience to Magistracy, not to men in that place<hi>:</hi> To press obedience hee tels us why we must obey: because ordained of God. To prevent mistakes, he shews what we must obey, viz. what God ordained, which are not the persons that are, but the power that are, as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by Presbyterians in speciall, as.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Whether Presbyterians who are already (but falsly) accused, to have laid the Kings head on the block for the Independants to cut it off, shall not now (it not by their sinfull silence) yet, if they do it by their shamefull complyance, &amp; concurrence with the progress and proceedings of these worst of times, justify their accusers, and condemn themselves, as guilty of that accusation?
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118714:6"/> and so most justly being upon themselves the odium of the worst that are and make themselves odious and abominable to all: and cause presbytery, it self, a way of God to be blasphemed? they had need to consider.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Whether <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who especially have been makers and takers of the <hi>Nationall Covenant,</hi> besides all those other <hi>oaths of God</hi> which are upon them, as <hi>Christians,</hi> and the <hi>duties of loyalty</hi> and <hi>subjection,</hi> and that for <hi>cons<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience sake,</hi> as they are <hi>subiects,</hi> I, <hi>Christian, Presbyterian subiects,</hi> ought not now to consider.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether they <hi>may</hi> with any good <hi>conscience</hi> and Christianity, joyn in <hi>counsel and communion</hi> with those whose counsels courses and constant acting, have been, are, and must be, (themselves must be ruined else) not only cross and contrary, but ruinous, and destructive to all these.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Whether themselves can walk in ways quite contrary to those <hi>oathes and covenants,</hi> they have taken and sworn, without being guilty of <hi>covenant breaking</hi> and <hi>for swearing,</hi> considering, <hi>that though conditionall oathes are bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding no further than the condition binds:</hi> as those in <hi>Gen.</hi> 24. 3. 5. 8. and in <hi>Josh.</hi> 2. 18, 19, 20, 21. yet that absolute <hi>oathes</hi> (which theirs are) taken without any condition at all, do bind absolutely, and cannot be broken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>periury,</hi> as is evident in the case of <hi>Zedekiah</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 36 11. 12, 13. with <hi>Ezek.</hi> 17.15. to 20. compared, and more evident in the case of <hi>Saul,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. 1, 2. where though the oath,</p>
            <p>1 Was gained by <hi>lying</hi> and <hi>deceit Josh,</hi> 9. 9. 2 was made with those, with whom the <hi>Isralites were forbid to make any, Exod.</hi> 23: 3<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 3. preserved those <hi>whom God had commanded should be destroyed. Deut.</hi> 7. 8. yet being made, <hi>was not, might not be broken Joshu.</hi> 9. 19 4 When it was broken, was broken by those <hi>who were not immediate makers of it.</hi> as 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. 1, 2. wtth <hi>Joshu.</hi> 9.15. compared. 5 VVas broken above 400. years after it was made, as <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 20. <hi>oaths</hi> then you see stand longer in force (400. years) then an old <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manack</hi> every year out of date: yet the breaking of this <hi>oath</hi> was <hi>severely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished,</hi> upon the <hi>breakers</hi> of it, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. 1, 2. 6 To these add <hi>that men are bound for breaking of oathes according to the binding of negative commandments;</hi> which bind, not only <hi>semper,</hi> but <hi>ad semper,</hi> the <hi>command,</hi> for not binding <hi>oathes,</hi> being given <hi>negatively,</hi> as the third Commandment, and <hi>Levit.</hi> 9.12. shew,</p>
            <p>3 Whether they must not, by committing these <hi>Sins,</hi> with <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dekiah,</hi> unavoidably bring upon themselves, <hi>their judgment</hi> and <hi>miseries?</hi> had not ne<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d pass without consideration</p>
            <p n="3">3 Whether i<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>may</hi> stand with <hi>Presbyterian prudence,</hi> that <hi>may and should be wise as Serpents,</hi> to repose any <hi>faith and confidence</hi> in to hope or promise any thing to themselves <hi>from such a person,</hi> in case there should be <hi>such a one in the world;</hi> scarce credible there can be any such, <hi>professing Christ amongst</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:118714:6"/>
               <hi>Christians,</hi> who hath already, not once but often, deceived all <hi>interests and parties</hi> whatsoever? &amp; whose <hi>principles</hi> &amp; <hi>practices</hi> have been, and are, to make use of all to set up, and uphold <hi>himself,</hi> and to hold up <hi>every thing, that,</hi> and nothing, but <hi>that,</hi> by which <hi>himself is upheld;</hi> who trusts neither <hi>partie,</hi> yet is afraid to <hi>displease either,</hi> because he must <hi>make use of both to do his work of self-advancing and upholding.</hi> The <hi>Presbyterian</hi> is for <hi>Magistracy,</hi> which the <hi>autimagistraticall Independant</hi> is not; therefore not <hi>policy</hi> if he would be the man, to displease the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> the <hi>Independant sword,</hi> when he is the man, can inable him to <hi>reign and rule,</hi> which the <hi>Presbyterian scabbord,</hi> cannot; therefore he must not in <hi>policy</hi> displease the <hi>Independant.</hi> Now whether to close with such a <hi>person</hi> that stands fast and faithfull to none, may stand with <hi>Presbyterian prudance,</hi> let <hi>Presbyterians well consider.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 Whether it will stand with <hi>Presbyterian loyalty to indulg the Thrown of iniquity?</hi> especially seeing <hi>presbyterians</hi> have in so many <hi>Declarations, Petitions, Protestations, oathes, and covenants</hi> pressed, professed protested, and with hands lifted up to the <hi>high God,</hi> sworn the contrary, <hi>let t<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em also well consider.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 Whether it <hi>can stand in Presbyterian piety,</hi> now <hi>with Independant sectaries</hi> to fall upon <hi>antipresbyterian pract<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ces in things most imp<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous,</hi> ought also to be considered? The way and work of <hi>Presbyterians</hi> (if right and real) hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been in <hi>sincerity, singleness, and truth of heart, to serve God in his providence</hi> for the accomplishing and fulfiilling of that <hi>gracious prophesie and promise,</hi> to be fulfilled in these last days. <hi>That the Lord shall be out, and his name one, Zech.</hi> 14. 9. Now whether to plough with an <hi>Ox, and an Ass to halt between two opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> to cool into a <hi>Laodecean luke warmness,</hi> to warm but into an <hi>anti-cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted cursed neutralite,</hi> and to daub <hi>with untempred morter</hi> by complying with a <hi>party that sets up Dagon by the Ark</hi> follows <hi>God and Baal,</hi> joyns <hi>light and darkness,</hi> and <hi>accords Christ with Beliall in setting up, or setitng such a Bastard Presbytery,</hi> as none <hi>truly fearing God,</hi> dares own, and such a <hi>licenticus liberty</hi> (for falsly so called) <hi>tender consciences,</hi> as every one that loves God, cannot but abominate, thereby to bring such a <hi>hocus pocus hotch potch of pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterated independancie, and independanted presbytery</hi> into the <hi>Church of God,</hi> as the <hi>Lord hates,</hi> and every Godly soul should from his <hi>soul abhor,</hi> (and this is the <hi>most,</hi> the <hi>best,</hi> the <hi>all,</hi> you must expect from such a party, I say whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to comply with such, and to own and accept this to be like to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish that <hi>promise,</hi> and if not, whether to walk in this way, can stand with <hi>Presbyterian pyety; let presbyterians sadly and seriously consider.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, by those that are to joyn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And first by those that have formerly been joyned in the l<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke counsel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. Whether it can be expected by any rational man, that they (both first and second company) that have already with shame and disgrace enough been
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118714:7"/> turned out of doors, if for doing unjustly, as their Masters which turned them out say, that they should now do justice? if for doing righteously, which the most doubt, (and fewest believe that they were then guilty of doing righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously) that they should now do any thing that is righteous, they sitting again under and by the same force and power which they did then; would by them be considered. 2. Whether they have yet unfainedly repented of those sins for which it is said, they <hi>were then turned out,</hi> [at least] <hi>by a just hand of God,</hi> whatever they were that turned them out? that they now once more imagin that the <hi>righteous Lord (who never makes use of wicked men to do any work for him, unless execution-work, Hab.</hi> 1.2) and who hath formerly refused them, when they were turned o<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; that <hi>he</hi> should now imploy them in any work of <hi>his,</hi> that is good for his <hi>Church and people,</hi> they had need consider.</p>
            <p>And secondly, <hi>By those that have formerly refused to joyn in such a counsel, or to act in or by any commission, or otherways, as Justices, Treasurers, Pleaders, Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strators &amp;c from by, or under the then impowred persons;</hi> let them consider, If their impowring was lawful, why they acted not then? if unlawful, it's the same, how they dare act now? and if their setting up was then illegal, how comes it now to be legitimate? if their refusing to act then was for conscience, as some imagined and others hoped, (but many thought there was no such thing as conscience by themselves thought of, in their non-acting) what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of conscience now, that they are not only willing to act, but desirously (though covertly) seek to be Actors in a business as illegal, and more sinful, than any of those they refused? and if they kept <hi>faith and a good conscience,</hi> by keeping from acting then, whether if now they act, they have not hit both; and are become like <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19, 20. and whether their present acting proceeds now from the <hi>new light of the times:</hi> enlightned at the <hi>clearest profit,</hi> the <hi>brightest preferment,</hi> and the most <hi>evident way to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent greatness,</hi> (the clearest light these men for the times, have ever seen or saw by) or from a principle of inward, sinful, self, soule, darkness, causing them to run after base <hi>honor,</hi> execrable <hi>mammon,</hi> and some other most ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly self end and interest; let these men now, of every of these in particular, wel consider. And Thirdly; <hi>By all that are to joyn in the counsel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 That it is unlawful, to do any (a lawful) work, without a lawful calling, being contrary to <hi>Luke</hi> 12.14. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.17. &amp; <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4 <hi>Ʋzziah</hi> his Leprosie evidently attest the truth of this that is said, &amp; the danger of those that do so.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That it is a sin expresly forbidden, so much asto meddle with wicked men at all in a <hi>wicked work, Exod.</hi> 23.27. and <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.21. and <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 6, 7, 11. and 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3, 4, 5. <hi>Jehosaphat</hi> his reproof proves this fully, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19, 2. and fals ful and flit upon them that do so</p>
            <p n="3">3 That this sin of <hi>joyning with wicked men in wickednes,</hi> contracts a double guilt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118714:7"/> 1 of sinning with others, reprov'd, <hi>Ps.</hi> 51.18— <hi>a theef, a traytor, an heretick, &amp;c.</hi> it holds in all; 2 of being partaker of others <hi>sins,</hi> forbidden, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5, 22. as ill, yea worse in an unlawful usurper, than in an unlawful minister, as the <hi>calling,</hi> so the <hi>sin</hi> the higher.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That is <hi>dangerous and destructive to joyn and meddle with wicked men in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedness; He that partakes with sinners in their sins, must be partaker with sinners in their sufferings,</hi> Rev. 18.4 &amp; Prov. 24.22, &amp; Num. 16.20.21, 26.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That the pretences pretended by vain men, to exempt themselves from <hi>sin,</hi> though they joyn in counsels and courses which they acknowledg <hi>sinfull,</hi> are more vanity and folly. 1 <hi>Ob.</hi> They are called by the <hi>people. Ans.</hi> 1 Not by the <hi>tenth part of the people.</hi> 3 But who called the people to call them? <hi>Sheba,</hi> z <hi>Sam</hi> zo. 1, z. And who called him to call them? He himself. And by what Law hath he called himself? By the same, by which <hi>Iereboams Priests made themselves priests, 1 King</hi> 1z. they made <hi>themselves priests of the high places,</hi> and he himself <hi>master of the highest place of Magistracy.</hi> Touching all which calls, consider, 1 That a <hi>self created calling,</hi> is like a <hi>self-created dignifying,</hi> which God long since stigmatized, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.7. z. That a calling by others, not lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called themselves, to call others, is as unwarrantable to warrant their <hi>Call,</hi> as Cyphers are ineffectual to make numbers without Figures. 3 That those <hi>persons</hi> which go upon such an unwarranted <hi>Call,</hi> their going is like the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of those <hi>Renegadoes</hi> God complains of, which ran and he sent them not, <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.21. So now, I hope, I may without offence, borrow the, Aposties words and say, <hi>Brethren, you see your calling how lawless and null it is. Ob.</hi> But they have good and honest intentions. <hi>Ans.</hi> To let pass; that this is one of the now <hi>Jesuited peoples arguments;</hi> how setled and sound this <hi>argumenn</hi> is, let <hi>Ʋzzab</hi> tel them in the second of <hi>Sam.</hi> 6: 6, 7. whose <hi>intentions</hi> I dare say for him, were as honest and good as theirs; and I think, <hi>Saul,</hi> as bad as he was, came nor far short in gooddess of their <hi>good intentions,</hi> when hee spared the best to <hi>sacrifice to the Lord,</hi> yet were they stark nought, if not as bad as <hi>witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crast.</hi> 3 <hi>Ob.</hi> But here is now a necessity, all else fals to ruin; the <hi>Schisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical party</hi> wil over-vote and ruin the Church, and the <hi>tyrannical party</hi> will over-power and destroy the <hi>Commonwealth. Ans: Nulla est necessitas delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendi, quibus una est necessitas non delinquendi:</hi> There can be no necessity to them to sin, to whom there is onely a necessity not to sin. He that can suffer cannot be necessitated to Sin<hi>:</hi> he that hath <hi>learned to live by faith, and knows whom he hath believed, and will deny himself to the taking up the Cross</hi> and dares trust God with what he hath, <hi>though God kill him, will not deliver him, and though he perish;</hi> such a one knows no necessity to sin, to save himselfe, or any thing els, because he knows, <hi>what he loseth he shall save; Mat.</hi> 16 25. 4 <hi>Ob.</hi> But here is a way open for them to do good, &amp;c. <hi>Ans.</hi> 1 Take need of doi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118714:8"/> evil to do good, their damnation is just that do so, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. 2 Take heed lest upon a bare hope (a hopeless hope) of doing good, you doe not that which will be a most certain evil<hi>:</hi> 1 Evil to another; if you support <hi>Athali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ah,</hi> (see 2 <hi>King</hi> 11) you must suppress <hi>Joash,</hi> and so spoil a man and his here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, evil indeep this, <hi>Mich.</hi> 2 2: 2 Evil to your selves, by bringing that just woe, by unjustly spoiling another, upon your selves, <hi>Mic.</hi> 22 i. 3 Evil to those, you say called you thither<hi>:</hi> If you be over-voted, be it in a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedness never so wicked, to the eternal enslaving of them and theirs, your presence concludes them slaves, which you absent, could not be. 4 Consider the improqability, if not the impossibility of doing good by four precedent presidents, 1 A legal Parliament, 2 A lawful King, 3 A Degenerated Juncto, 4 An illegal congregated company. Neither any, nor all of these could; and then, what possibility that you, every way inferiour to the most of them, if not to the meanest, if not in parts, yet in piety, loyalty, legality and fidelity, should do any good at all? more probable a world of mischief to your selves and all other:</p>
            <p n="6">6 It is still to be considered by themselve (and others too) the premises considered, whether they that think themseves, and are thought by some others, men wise enough to manage such a work, a work of deepest difficulty and highest concernment, yet plead such poor pretences, and produce such unreasonable reasons to excuse themselves in doing that, by doing which they must unavoidably pull such sins upon themselves, and such misery upon others: I say whether they are indeed and truth men fit to be trusted with such a depositum and trust, as usually and safely hath been laid up in a loyal legall and lawfull Parliament concerning the glory of God, the honor of the Gospel, the safety of three Kingdomes, and the choysest, chiefest com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of so many thousand thousands souls, I say again this had need be well considered.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Whether any act of 2. or 3 hundred, a few in comparison of those many thousands, I thousand thousands of others, every one of which, being as much concerned in, and having as good right unto any thing they do in these things of publique concernment as any of them<hi>:</hi> and this minor part as far inferior in quality and condition, as in number, being mean and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable in comparison of the gentility, and nobility of some thousands of the otherts and these both minor and meaner part, not having any lawfull calling at all to do any thing they do. I say whether they can do any act, that can in it self be legal and valid in the Law, and have any thing in it of truth justice and righteousness, which can be binding any way to al or any of the other, without whose consents, if not contrary to the wil and minds of the most of them, they have done what they have done, would also be consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118714:8"/>
            <p> Fourthly, and lastly, <hi>By Ministers; and so had they need to consider.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Whether that Minister who hath taken upon him the work of a <hi>Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> and doth not give warning to the people (for the safety of whose souls<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ought to watch) of the comming of the wolf, <hi>(which every sin is)</hi> where by the <hi>people</hi> perish, <hi>shall not have the peoples blood,</hi> required at his hand? let <hi>such consider</hi> Ezek. 3. and 33. Chap. and let them further <hi>consider,</hi> that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, usurpation, tyrany, perjury, and heresie, may for their <hi>fierceness</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structiveness, be truly said to be <hi>Wolves of the evening,</hi> as <hi>Hab.</hi> 1. 8: saith of the like.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Whether that Minister which knows not the <hi>Wolfe</hi> when he <hi>comes,</hi> but takes, rather mistakes him for a <hi>Lamb</hi> be not one of those whom Christ <hi>calls blinde leaders of the blinde: Mat.</hi> 15. 14. And if he do know him, yet leads along, and goeth before the people unto the <hi>Wolfe:</hi> be not one of those, the Lord by his prophet Complained of, the leaders of my people; Cause them to <hi>Isa.</hi> 9. 16 <hi>let such consider.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether that Minister which preacheth onely or mostly the pleaseing things of <hi>promises, graces, liberties,</hi> the way they tel us to preach Christ to <hi>salvation;</hi> yet in the midst of most wicked and abominable ways of notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wicked men, walking in treason, rebellion, perjury, tyranny, heresy and the like; with which there is of the most, either a Sinful Concurre<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce, or Connivance, but yet doth seldome or never cry aloud against those <hi>crying sins</hi> of these times, the high-way to condemnation; doth or can by so doing, shew himself faithful in his <hi>Ministery,</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> to his own <hi>soul,</hi> and the souls of the <hi>people;</hi> such a Minister had need wel to <hi>consider.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Seeing it is most certain, that obedience to the <hi>higher power,</hi> and to persons <hi>lawfully impowred,</hi> is by the <hi>people</hi> to be performed for Conscience, <hi>Rom</hi> 13.51 and that a <hi>consciencious obedience</hi> is contained in, and held out by the Word of God; it is not <hi>perfect else, which it is,</hi> Psa. 19. 7 and is part of that <hi>whole counsel</hi> of God, which none shun to <hi>declare, Act.</hi> 20. 20, 27. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Minister which doth not <hi>declare</hi> this part of Gods <hi>counsel, (touching this obedience for conscience)</hi> as wel as any other, especially when it wil be a word in season, doth not <hi>preach Christ to the halves?</hi> whether in so doing, he doth make <hi>ful proof of his Ministery,</hi> and shew <hi>hemself</hi> approved of God, a workman that needeth not to be ashamed, or the Contrary? should by Ministers now in these times be seriously and sadly <hi>considered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether <hi>such Ministers</hi> which formerly refused to Contribute towards making of a War, to <hi>force</hi> upon our brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> but the use of a Common prayer Book, as but derogatory from, or dangerous to that pure worship of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Church-Descipline</hi> there established by Law amongst them and for refuseing thereof stood out a suspention? <hi>yet doe,</hi> and <hi>can now comply</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:118714:9"/>
               <hi>with,</hi> and give <hi>assistance</hi> to those that have upon the matter wholly destroyed out brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> and our selves also, not onely in both those, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most in all things els of highest pious publike Concernment, are not such as we find amongst those, against whom Christ denounced so many woes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.24 <hi>which diastrain at agnat, and swallow down a Camel?</hi> Let <hi>such Ministers</hi> lay to heart, and Consider wel of it.</p>
            <p>For a CONCLVSION: <hi>If Ministers laying aside servile fear and base couetousness. would declare their consciences according to the word of</hi> God<hi>: And Lawyers without halting on the same sores, would deliver their judgments accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the known</hi> Laws <hi>of this Land: And if every one that exalts him<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elfe would be brought under the obedience of Christ, Conscience might quickly be satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied touching all these</hi> Considerations and Queries. <hi>By which (in all places] the oppressed might be restored to his right, the oppressor might be brought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, these three Kingdomes might be setled in peace and truth, and above all to be desired,</hi> God <hi>might be glorified. Towards the happy effecting of all which, let some act, some pray, and all say Amen: and let every one that loveth the Lord</hi> Jesus Christ <hi>in truth, take these and the like Considerations and Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries into his most serious consideration.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:118714:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>